<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xml>
    <name>Country Loaf (Pain de Campagne)</name>

    <author>Deb Lindsey for The Washington Post</author>

    <date when="2014-09-10">SEP 10, 2014</date>
    <note>Washington author Sam Fromartz has been making sourdough variations of this yeast bread
        for years. Here, he adds fermented cider for flavor. A mild beer may be substituted; an IPA
        would be too bitter. The loaf is sized to last a few days. The optional tablespoon of water
        is to compensate for the variable absorption of the rye and whole-wheat flours. You'll need
        a colander, a pastry cloth or clean dish towel and a covered cast-iron or enameled cast-iron
        pot. Make Ahead: The dough needs four 20-minute rests, plus an 8-to-24-hour stay in the
        refrigerator and a final 1 1/2-hour rise. Storage Notes: Store the cooled loaf in a paper
        bag for a day, and store in a plastic bag for a few days after that. Do not
        refrigerate.</note>

    <servings> SERVINGS: Tested size: <n type="whole">10</n>-<n type="whole">12</n> servings; makes
        one <n type="whole">11</n>-ounce loaf <n type="whole">10</n> to <n type="whole">12</n>
        slices</servings>

    <ingredients>INGREDIENTS <line/><n type="whole">1</n><n type="fraction" dec=".25">1/4</n> cups
            (<n type="whole">160</n> grams) <ing>white bread flour</ing>, plus more for dusting <n
            type="fraction" dec=".25">1/4</n> cup (<n type="whole">38</n> grams)
            <line/><ing>stone-ground whole-wheat flour</ing>
        <line/><n type="fraction" dec=".25">1/4</n> cup (<n type="whole">32</n> grams)
            <line/><ing>stone-ground whole rye flour</ing>
        <line/><n type="whole">1/2</n> teaspoon <ing>instant yeast</ing> or <ing>bread machine
            yeast</ing>
        <line/><n type="whole">1</n> teaspoon <ing>table salt</ing>
        <line/><n type="fraction" dec=".25">1/4</n> cup (<n type="whole">55</n> grams) <line/>
        <ing>dry fermented cider</ing>
        <note>(may substitute Pilsener beer; see headnote)</note>
        <line/><n type="fraction" dec=".5">1/2</n> cup <line/>(<n type="whole">120</n> grams)
            <ing>lukewarm water</ing> (80 degrees), plus an optional 1 tablespoon</ingredients>
    <directions>DIRECTIONS <line/><task num="1">Whisk together the flours, yeast and salt in a
            mixing bowl. Combine the cider and water in a liquid measuring cup.</task>
        <line/>
        <task num="2">Add the liquid to the flour mixture; use a spatula or bench scraper or your
            hand moistened with water to blend them for about a <time/>minute. The dough should be
            shaggy yet cohesive. Cover the bowl with a towel; let the dough rest for <time><n
                    type="whole">20</n> minutes</time>.</task>
        <line/><task num="3">Moisten your kneading hand. If the dough seems stiff, add the optional
            tablespoon of water. Stretch one edge of the dough (still in the bowl), then press it
            into the center of the bowl. Repeat this about a dozen times, moving clockwise to catch
            all sides of the dough. (This should take <time><n type="whole">1</n> or <n type="whole"
                    >2</n> minutes</time>.)</task>
        <line/><task num="4">Turn the dough over so the seams are on the bottom. Cover and let rest
            for <n type="whole">20</n> minutes. Repeat the clockwise stretching and folding two more
            times, with <time><n type="whole">20</n>-minute</time> rests after each. Cover and
            refrigerate at least <time><n type="whole">8</n> hours</time> and up to <time><n
                    type="whole">24</n> hours</time>. The dough should have doubled. If it hasn't,
            leave it on the counter until it does.</task>
        <line/>
        <task num="5">Lightly flour a work surface. Use a pastry cloth or clean dish towel to line a
            round colander. Dust the cloth with flour.</task>
        <line/><task num="6">Transfer the dough to the floured work surface. Fold the edges toward
            the center to create a round shape, turning it over so the seams are on the bottom. Let
            it rest for <time><n type="whole">5</n> minutes</time>, then transfer to the colander,
            seam side up. Cover with a towel and let the dough rise for <time><n type="whole">1</n>
                <n type="fraction" dec=".25">1/2</n> hours</time>.</task>
        <line/>
        <task num="7">Thirty minutes before baking, place a cast-iron Dutch oven (lid on) or
            enameled cast-iron pot with a lid (on) in the oven; preheat to <temp><n type="whole"
                    >475</n> degrees</temp>.</task>
        <line/><task num="8">Carefully remove the hot pot from the oven.</task>
        <line/><task num="9">Turn the dough out onto the counter so the seams are on the bottom. Use
            kitchen scissors to make <n type="whole">8</n> snips on the top of the dough in an
            evenly spaced spoke pattern, each about <meas><n type="fraction" dec=".25">1/4</n>-inch</meas>
            deep. Lift the dough and carefully drop it into the hot pot. Immediately cover with the
            hot lid. Bake for <time><n type="whole">30</n> minutes</time>, then reduce the heat to
                    <temp><n type="whole">450</n> degrees</temp>. Uncover and bake for <time><n
                    type="whole">8</n> to <n type="whole">10</n> minutes</time> or until the crust
            is dark brown. Try to minimize the amount of time the oven door is open.</task>
        <line/><task num="10">The bread is done when its internal temperature registers <temp><n
                    type="whole">205</n> degrees</temp> on an instant-read thermometer and the loaf
            sounds hollow when knocked on the underside.</task>
        <line/><task num="11">Transfer the loaf to a wire rack to cool for at least <time><n
                    type="whole">1</n> hour</time> before cutting.</task></directions>
</xml>
